Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Computer Science, Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series, Videorecordings V0058
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings
  - Betting, Bribery, and Bankruptcy: Organizing Computation Around Simulated Free Enterprise, Ted Kaehler, 1988-11-16; V0058.118; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    Objects inside a computer exchange money for work and information in the course of solving a problem. When designing a monetary incentive system for computational entities, it helps to think of them as "bad" or "uncooperative.
  - Vectors are History, Forest Baskett, 1988-11-30; V0058.119; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box not specified)
    In this talk we give a few technology-independent methods for assessing the architectural effectiveness of existing vector processors and scalar processors. We show the progress of scalar processor architectures over the last ten years and show how they are now surpassing vector processor architectures in terms of architectural effectiveness on vectorizable as well as non-vectorizable scientific and engineering applications. We illustrate this current state by comparing the actual performance of our Silicon Graphics Iris 4D1240 scalar multiprocessor with the performance of some other vector multiprocessors. In closing we illustrate the critical importance of block method algorithms for achieving the performance potential of most current scalar processors.
  - Compiling for a Memory Hierarchy, Rob Schreiber, 1988-10-12; V0058.120; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    In this talk we explore the use of a two-level memory hierarchy having a large, shared, relatively slow level and a small, distributed, relatively fast level. This scheme has the potential for exploiting the advantages of both shared and distributed memory systems. But to exploit it, programs must make most of their references to the fast, distributed memory. Block algorithms are a powerful tool for exploiting this memory architecture. In this talk we present a general compiler technique for automatically "blocking" algorithms. The problem is reduced to a simple geometric computation.
  - XTPIPE Overview, Greg Chesson, 1988-10-26; V0058.121; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 21)
    XTP is a new network protocol under development for the last few years which is being incorporated into new ANSI and U.S. Government network standards. It is designed to perform network gateway functions as well as end-to-end transport functions. It provides for reliable multicasting, transactions, selective retransmission, parameterized addressing, delivery confirmation, and reliable datagrams, as well as traditional bulk and stream services. These services are implemented with simple algorithms that can be rendered in VLSI circuits. The Protocol Engine is a chip set designed to operate XTP in real time.
- Additional Videorecordings, 1980-1987
  - Software Controlled Caches in the VMP Multiprocessor, David Cheriton, 1986-10-08; V0058.122; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 22)
    VMP is an experimental multiprocessor that follows the familiar basic design of multiple processors, each with a cache, connected by a shared bus to global memory. Each processor has a synchronous, virtually addressed, single master connection to its cache, providing very high memory bandwidth. An unusually large cache page size and fast sequential memory copy hardware make it feasible for cache misses to be handled in software, analogously to the handling of virtual memory page faults. Hardware support for cache consistency is limited to a simple state machine that monitors the bus and interrupts the processor when a cache consistency action is required. In this talk, we describe how the VMP design provides the high memory bandwidth required by modern high-performance processors with a minimum of hardware complexity and cost. We also describe simple solutions to the consistency problems associated with virtually addressed caches. Simulation results indicate that the design achieves good performance providing data contention is not excessive.
  - Xerox Personal Research Computers, Edward McCreight, 1980-10-22; V0058.123; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    Between 1973 and 1980, three microprogrammable 16-bit personal computers were developed at the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center. Divided into control, arithmetic, memory, macroinstruction-decoding, and I/O sections, the architectures of these computers are explained, compared, and contrasted.
  - A High Level Approach to Computer Document Production, Brian K. Reid, 1980-12-03; V0058.124; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    People spend an outrageous amount of time using computers to format their documents. There are two possible explanations for this: the great importance of the task, or the inappropriateness of the standard tools. SCRIBE is a stab at building more appropriate tools: it was not designed to produce beautiful output, but to accept beautiful input. The SCRIBE system was designed around the principle that all good software should deal with the problem domain at as high a level of abstraction as possible, and around the underlying assumption that although users don't want to become experts, everybody wants to tinker. To these ends, SCRIBE is a high-level non-procedural table-drive system, with an extensive facility for making modifications to its behavior without needing to understand the programming issues behind them.
  - The Architecture and Implementation of the Intel 432, Justin Rattner, 1981-02-25; V0058.125; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    The Intel 432 is a recently introduced microcomputer system designed to support very large scale software (VLSS) systems. In order to better serve software-intensive microcomputer applications, the 432 departs significantly from existing mainframe mini- and microcomputer designs. Examples of this departure include the 432's high-level, object-based architecture and its flexible multiprocessor system organization. This talk will briefly review the motivations and concepts that underlie the 432 and will then take up its object-based architecture and VLSI implementation.
  - High Speed Operation of Local Area Networks, John Limb, 1982-02-13; V0058.126; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 23)
    Local Communication Networks need large transmission capacities to handle all traffic in the evolving business environment (e.g., data, voice, facsimile and video). He first compares the high speed performance of two bi-directional CSMA protocols; one very popular and the other very efficient. A unidirectional system using a passive medium (called FASNET) will be described and compared with the other two systems.
  - High Speed Operation of Local Area Networks, John Limb, 1982-02-13; V0058.127; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 23)
  - A Retrospective on the Dorado, a High-Performance Personal Computer, Kenneth Pier, 1982-04-14; V0058.128; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic) (Box 23)
    Between 1975 and 1980, a high performance personal computer caller Dorado was conceived, designed, implemented and produced within Xerox PARC. The Dorado supports sophisticated single user programming environments in several high level languages including Lisp, Smalltalk, and Mesa. High bandwidth input/output devices, including color displays and networks, are supported as well. This is a retrospective on the properties, successes, and failures of the Dorado project, with an emphasis on the architecture and implementation of the machine. A review of the architecture opens the talk, followed by comments on specific sections introduced in the review. Finally, there is an overall evaluation and some speculation on the past and the future of Dorado-like architectures.
  - Locus Developments, Gerald J. Popek, 1982-02-10; V0058.129; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    Locus is a distributed operating system, operational at UCLA, that provides a high degree of network transparency, both for data and processes. It provides a system call interface compatible with Unix, and permits a wide degree of resource allocation decisions, including support for diskless machines, replicated storage, etc. The Locus architecture will be briefly reviewed, and then recent developments and ongoing work will be outlined. These include experience with and limits to transparency, a low cost approximation to nested transactions, approaches to heterogeneity, and the boundary between transparence and local autonomy.
  - The Optical Mouse and an Architectural Methodology for Smart Digital Sensors, Richard Lyon, 1982-10-06; V0058.130; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    A mouse is a pointing device used with interactive computer systems. Electromechanical mice were first developed in the 60s at SRI. The mechanical mouse was redesigned at Xerox and has been in popular use there for several years. To overcome a number of observed problems with the mechanical mouse, work was started in the 1980s on an optical replacement for the electromechanical mouse. This talk describes the design and tenting of the prototype optical mouse.
  - The SUN Workstation, Andreas Bechtolsheim, 1982-11-09; V0058.131; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    The SUN Workstation is a desk-top personal computer system, combining mainframe processing power, Ethernet networking, and a high-speed raster graphics display with 1024 by 800 pixel resolution. Designed around a 32-bit microprocessor, the Motorola 68010, the SUN Workstation provides approximately 1 MIPS processor performance, multiprocess memory management, virtual memory capabilities, and a physical memory of 1 MByte or more. One of the software environments now being ported to the SUN Workstation is the Berkeley 4.2bsd UNIX operating system. This provides the same software environment on the SUN Workstation now available for the Digital Equipment VAX computer family, together with the ability to run SUN Workstations without local mass storage from remote fileservers. The talk focuses on the system architecture and the implementation of the SUN Workstation. Statistics and history of the project are discussed, and a demonstration is included.
  - Database and Distributed Systems Research, Robin Williams, 1983-01-11; V0058.132; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    There are several database projects in IBM Research, San Jose, including work on distributed database systems, on high availability, on high performance and on databases for engineering design. Descriptions will be give of these activities with a concentration on R*, a distributed database system, which is now a working prototype, running on three IBM 4341 machines. R* is a confederation of co-operating sites each supporting the relational model of data. To achieve maximum site autonomy, statements in the language SQL are compiled, data objects are named and catalogued, and deadlock detention and recovery are all handled in a distributed manner. The R* architecture is presented.
  - A High-Performance Implementation of Smalltalk-80™, Allan M. Schiffman, 1983-01-12; V0058.133; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 23)
    The programming language and environment Smalltalk-80 has been implemented on a variety of processors. The talk describes yet another implementation on a commercially-available microprocessor system (the SUN workstation). The details of the implementation are of interest since significant performance improvements have been obtained without sacrificing the existing semantics of Smalltalk. A preliminary version of the system has been benchmarked. In several significant departures from the implementation suggestions of the Smalltalk virtual-machine designers, our implementation has achieved substantial performance improvements. The overall design strategy has been summed up – "The implementer must cheat, but not get caught." We can group the majority of the departures under the headings of "dynamic translation" and "optimized contexts." These techniques could be applied to implementations of languages other than Smalltalk.
  - Packet Network Interconnection Standards, Vint Cerf, 1983-02-01; V0058.134; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    This talk provides an overview of the history of packet switching. Relevant packet-switching technology will be reviewed, including packet radio, packet satellite, local networks, and terrestrial packet networks such as the ARPANET. We will then review network interconnection techniques leading to the present Department of Defense packet protocol standards, collectively referred to as the ARPA internet protocols.
  - The Cedar Systems: Perspectives and Projections, Roy Levin, 1983-02-08; V0058.135; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    The Cedar system is an experimental programming environment for the "D" machines (Dorado, Dolphin, Dandelion). The language and system have been heavily influenced by other local programming systems, notably Mesa, Star, Smalltalk, and Interlisp. Consequently, it emphasizes integration of programming and non-programming tools in an environment tuned to rapid production of experimental software. This talk includes a brief review of the origins and goals of the Cedar project, a description of the present status, and a sketch of the probable development over the next couple of years. In the process, the talk focuses on the features of the system that are unique or unusual in Algol-tradition programming environments.
  - Evidential Reasoning in Perception, John D. Lowrance, 1983-02-22; V0058.136; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    One common feature of my perceptual system is that it must reason based upon the evidential information that is provided by its sensors. Expert-system technology would seem to provide a mechanism for reasoning from evidence, yet there is very little agreement on how this should be done. Here we present our current understanding of this problem and some partial solutions. We begin by characterizing evidence as a body of information that is uncertain, incomplete, and sometimes inaccurate. Based on this characterization, we conclude that evidential reasoning requires both a method for pooling multiple bodies of evidence to arrive at a consensus opinion and some means of drawing the appropriate conclusions from that opinion. We contrast our approach, based on a relatively new mathematical theory of evidence, with those approaches based on Bayesian probability models. We believe that our approach has some significant advantages, particularly its ability to represent and reason from bounded ignorance. The specific problem addressed is that of multi-modal perception, particularly the integration of sensory information with prior world knowledge, in order to assess relevant aspects of the current environment. A prototype system has been constructed that demonstrates the utility of these techniques.
  - Rediflow: A Multiprocessing Architecture Combining Reduction and Data Flow, Robert M. Keller, 1983-05-10; V0058.137; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    Functional languages, i.e., languages based upon composition of functions rather than upon sequences of commands, have been conjectured to be useful in making the power of multiple processors more accessible. We demonstrate the utility of the functional approach within application domains such as logic programming and database updating. Two principle types of evaluation model, reduction and dataflow, have been proposed for highly-concurrent evaluation of functional languages. After pointing out the relative advantages of each type, we indicate how the two can profitably be combined. We then describe a proposal for Rediflow, a multiprocessor architecture based on the combined model, which also features system-managed distribution of tasks to processing elements.
  - How Fast Can a Single Instruction Counter Machine Execute?, Tilak Agerwala, 1983-05-24; V0058.138; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    After a brief overview of the limitations of conventional pipelined processors and vector processors, this talk describes recent work at IMB Research on very high speed scalar machines. Our goal was the paper design of a machine that could sustain a speed of roughly 100 million instructions per second on general purpose scientific/engineering applications, with peak floating point performance of roughly 100 million floating point operations per second. The talk will identify the extent to which these goals were achieved and the combination of compiler, machine organization, and architecture approaches used. The chosen design point represents a new partitioning of work between the complier and the hardware. The talk will discuss the performance achievable by internally concurrent, "single instruction counter machines" and will compare our approach to others such as long instruction work computers and data flow.
  - Software Army on the March – Project Strategies and Tactics, John R. Mashey, 1983-09-28; V0058.139; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
    This talk describes the work of an army building roads as an analogy to software projects. Decision-making processes are examined from two different viewpoints. The first is the formal game theory viewpoint – making decisions in a non-deterministic, multi-state, non-zero-sum game played with incomplete information. The second is the "army" model. From this viewpoint are discussed such issues as: fighting the right war in the right place and choosing good routes to reach the goals; the need for scouts on motorcycles ("fast prototypers"); how campaigns differ, and thus affect choice of troops; special precautions for earthquake country; getting natives to buy and drive your trucks, instead of shooting your tires out as you drive through their villages. There exist many similarities in the decision processes of formal game analysis, military planning, and project management. The talk uses the first and second to help shed light on the third.
  - The Human Factor: Designing Computer Systems for People, Dick Rubinstein, 1984-06-05; V0058.140; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
    What principles of human factors – and what just plain good ideas – may be applied to the design of quality user interfaces? Dr. Rubinstein advances a number of principles and ideas that can make computer systems better for all users, including examples from the VAXstation user interface.
  - Belief, Awareness and Limited Reasoning, Joe Halpern, 1985-10-01; V0058.141; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - Perceptual Organization and the Representation of Natural Form, Alex P. Pentland, 1985-11-19; V0058.142; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - A Knowledge-Based Approach to High-Level Program Optimization, Allen Goldberg, 1985-12-10; V0058.143; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - Technology Trends of CMOS VLSI, Yoshio Nishi, 1986-01-22; V0058.144; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - Lattices and Algorithms, Laszlo Lovasz, 1986-02-18; V0058.145; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - An Introduction to the Probabilistic Analysis of Combinatorial Algorithms, Richard Karp, 1987-05-19; V0058.146; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 24)
  - Adaptive Mesh Refinement for Hyperbolic Partial Differential Equations, Marsha J. Berger, 1982-07-07; V0058.147; 1 videotape(s) (U-matic) (Box 24)
    In many time dependent simulations, the solution on most of the domain will be fairly smooth, with discontinuities or highly oscillatory phenomena occurring over only a small fraction of the domain. In problems such as these, a mesh refinement approach can be the most efficient, and often the only practical solution method. Refined grids with smaller and smaller mesh spacing are placed only where they are needed. Since we are solving a time dependent problem, the regions needing refinement will change, and therefore our grids must adapt with time as well. This thesis presents a method based on the idea of multiple, component grids for the solution of hyperbolic partial differential equations (pde) using explicit finite difference techniques. Using Richardson-type estimates of the local truncation error, refined grids are created or existing ones removed to attain a given accuracy for a minimum amount of work. In addition, this approach is recursive in that fine grids can themselves contain even finer subgrids. Those grids with finer mesh width in space will also have a smaller mesh width in time, making this a mesh refinement algorithm in time and space.
  - Pamphlet to accompany talk by A. R. Stivers, Voltage Contrast: A Powerful Tool for VLSI Circuit Diagnosis, V0058.148 (Box 24)
- Additional Videorecordings, Accession ARCH-2017-023
- Duplicate Videorecordings, Accession ARCH-2001-332
  - Numbers 1-12, 14, 18-19 (Box 1)
  - Numbers 25, 28, 32-34, 37-40, 42-46 (Box 2)
  - Numbers 47-52, 54-61 (Box 3)
  - Numbers 62-72 and Lectures of special interest A and C – E (Box 4)
  - Lectures of special interest F – I (Box 5)
- Additional Videorecordings, 1981-1998; Accession ARCH-2017-023
  - Computer Forum Presents Mach: The OS of the Next Computer. Avadis Tevanian, NEXT, undated; V0058_149; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Stanford Computer Forum Distinguished Lecture Series: Knowledge Engineering (Japanese Translation), undated; V0058_150; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - The Stanford Computer Forum Presents: Matt Rhodes - "Restructureable ULSI for Water Scale Integration", undated; V0058_151; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Forum Video, undated; V0058_152; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Forum Overview Video: Stanford Computer Forum, undated; V0058_153; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Stanford Computer Forum Presents: Mark Linton--"Inter Views: A C++ Graphical Interface Toolkit", undated; V0058_154; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Stanford Computer Forum Presents: The Cydra 5: A Directed-dataflow Departmental Supercomputer/Bob Rau, 1988-10-5; V0058_155; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum Presents: Systems Day on Campus: Dennis Allison- "Architecture-Directed Code Optimization", 1989-6-8; V0058_156; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum Presents: Systems Day on Campus: David Ungar- "Self: A High-Performance Object-Oriented Dynamically Typed Exploratory Programming Language", 1989-6-8; V0058_157; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum Presents: AI and Technology. Stanford AI Day on Campus., 1990-6; V0058_158; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum Presents: AI, the Brain, and Society. Stanford AI Day on Campus., 1990-6; V0058_159; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum Presents: Agent-Centered Reasoning. Stanford AI Day on Campus., 1990-6; V0058_160; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - The Stanford Computer Forum Presents: Time in the Human-Computer Interface. Dr Chuck Clanton, Aratar, 1981-5-29; V0058_161; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - The Stanford Computer Forum Presents: S-D-O-C with Professors Olukotun, Flynn, Mitchell (Tape 2), 1992-6-11; V0058_162; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - The Stanford Computer Forum Video Journal: Heterogeneous Multidatabase Systems, 1992; V0058_163; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Stanford Computer Forum Presents: Systems Day on Campus, undated; V0058_164; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - The Stanford Computer Forum Presents: "Designing High Performance Circuits or What Mead and Conway Never Told You" Mark Horowitz, undated; V0058_165; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Computer Forum-Affiliate Testimony, undated; V0058_166; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Stanford Computer Forum: CS Department Overview, undated; V0058_167; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - CS Annual Forum Meeting Panel Discussion, 1998-3-19; V0058_168; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - CS Annual Forum Meeting Panel Discussion, 1998-3-19; V0058_169; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - CSci 8899: Computer Science Colloquium: Convergence Architecture and the Stanford FLASH Machine, Dr. John Hennessy, Stanford, 1998 Apr 6; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)